{
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following sentence sequences creates a coherent narrative?<br>\n<br>(i) Once on the terrace, on her way to her small room in the corner, she\nnotices the man right away.\n<br>(ii) She begins to pant by the time she has climbed all the stairs.\n<br>(iii) Mina has bought vegetables and rice at the market, so her bags are\nheavy.\n<br>(iv) He was leaning against the parapet, watching the traffic below. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i), (ii), (iv), (iii)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(ii), (iii), (i), (iv)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(iv), (ii), (i), (iii)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii), (ii), (i), (iv)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii), (ii), (i), (iv)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399248/gate-cse-2023-ga-question8#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Kind : _______ : : Often : Frequently<br>\n(By word meaning) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mean</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Type</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Cruel</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Kindly</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Type</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399254/gate-cse-2023-ga-question2#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>We reached the station late, and _______ missed the train. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>near</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>nearly</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>utterly</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>mostly</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>nearly</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399255/gate-cse-2023-ga-question1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The corners and mid-points of the sides of a triangle are named using the distinct letters P, Q, R, S, T and U, but not necessarily in the same order. Consider the following statements:\n<br><br>\nThe line joining P and R is parallel to the line joining Q and S.<br> P is placed on the side opposite to the corner T.\n<br> S and U cannot be placed on the same side.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements is correct based on the above information? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>S cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>U cannot be placed at a mid-point</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R cannot be placed at a corner</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>S cannot be placed at a corner</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371497/Gate-cse-2022-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Some people believe that \"what gets measured, improves\". Some others believe that \"what gets measured, gets gamed\". One possible reason for the difference in the beliefs is the work culture in organizations. In organizations with good work culture, metrics help improve outcomes. However, the same metrics are counterproductive in organizations with poor work culture.\n<br>\nWhich one of the following is the CORRECT logical inference based on the information in the above passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with poor work culture</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with good work culture</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Metrics are always counterproductive in organizations with good work culture</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Metrics are never useful in organizations with good work culture</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Metrics are useful in organizations with good work culture</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371500/Gate-cse-2022-question-6#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Given below are four statements. <br><br>Statement 1: All students are inquisitive. <br>Statement 2: Some students are inquisitive. <br>Statement 3: No student is inquisitive.\n<br>Statement 4: Some students are not inquisitive.\n<br><br>\nFrom the given four statements, find the two statements that CANNOT BE TRUE simultaneously, assuming that there is at least one student in the class. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Statement 2 and Statement 4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Statement 3 and Statement 4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Statement 1 and Statement 3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371502/Gate-cse-2022-question-4#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>The _____ is too high for it to be considered ______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2022)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fair / fare</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>faer / fair</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fare / fare</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>fare / fair</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>fare / fair</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/371505/Gate-cse-2022-ga-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Six students P, Q, R, S, T and U, with distinct heights, compare their heights and make the following observations.<br><br>\nObservation I: S is taller than R.<br>\nObservation II: Q is the shortest of all.<br>\nObservation III: U is taller than only one student.<br>\nObservation IV: T is taller than S but is not the tallest<br><br>\nThe number of students that are taller than R is the same as the number of students shorter than ____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>S</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>S</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357540/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-10#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Listening to music during exercise improves performance and reduces discomfort. Scientists researched whether listening to music while studying can help students learn better and the results were inconclusive. Students who needed external stimulation for studying fared worse while students who did not need any external stimulation benefited from music.<br><br>\nWhich one of the following statements is the CORRECT inference of the above passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Listening to music has no effect on learning and a positive effect on physical exercise</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect both in physical exercise and on learning</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on physical exercise. Music has a positive effect on learning only in some students</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on learning in all students. Music has a positive effect only in some students who exercise</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Listening to music has a clear positive effect on physical exercise. Music has a positive effect on learning only in some students</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357544/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Pen : Write :: Knife :  _______<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options maintains a similar logical relation in the above? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Vegetables</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Sharp</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Cut</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Blunt</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Cut</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357545/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-5#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Gauri said that she can play the keyboard __________ her sister. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>as well as</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>as better as</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>as nicest as</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>as worse as</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>as well as</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357549/gate-cse-2021-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Some people suggest anti-obesity measures (AOM) such as displaying calorie information in restaurant menus. Such measures sidestep addressing the core problems that cause obesity: poverty and income inequality.<br><br>Which one of the following statements summarizes the passage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The proposed AOM addresses the core problems that cause obesity</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If obesity reduces, poverty will naturally reduce, since obesity causes poverty</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the core problems and are likely to succeed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the problem superficially</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>AOM are addressing the problem superficially</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357467/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-10#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Given below are two statements 1 and 2, and two conclusions I and II<br><br>\nStatement 1: All bacteria are microorganisms.<br>\nStatement 2: All pathogens are microorganisms.<br><br>\nConclusion I: Some pathogens are bacteria.<br>\nConclusion II: All pathogens are not bacteria.<br><br>\nBased on the above statements and conclusions, which one of the following options is logically CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only conclusion I is correct</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only conclusion II is correct</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Either conclusion I or II is correct</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither conclusion I nor II is correct</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither conclusion I nor II is correct</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357468/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-9#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>There are five bags each containing identical sets of ten distinct chocolates. One chocolate is picked from each bag.\n<br>\nThe probability that at least two chocolates are identical is _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.3024</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.4235</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.6976</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.8125</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.6976</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357469/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-8#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>_________ is to surgery as writer is to ___________\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options maintains a similar logical relation in the above sentence? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Plan, outline</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Hospital, library</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Doctor, book</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Medicine, grammar</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Doctor, book</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357472/gate-cse-2021-set-1-ga-question-5#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}